PINAKI DUTTA

Buffalo, NY ● (848) 256-2883 ● pinakidu@buffalo.edu ● https://www.linkedin.com/in/pinakid/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Dedicated IT Financial Data Analyst with over 10 years of experience in PMO, Finance, Data, and Technology Business Management (TBM). Collaborated with cross-functional teams across the organization, including key stakeholders and customers, to define project scope, resource requirements, budget, timeline, deliverables, and milestones.

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY AT BUFFALO, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK

Master of Business Administration

Jun. 2023

Concentration: Finance, GPA: 3.751/4.00

Relevant Courses - Business Strategy, Financial Accounting for Managers, Accounting for Decision-Making, Financial
Analysis for Managers, IT for Managers, Investment Management, International Finance Management, M&A Strategy,
Financial Modeling, Fixed Income Securities, Multinational Banking, Data Modeling, Database Management System

SRM INSTITUTE OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY, CHENNAI, INDIA

Bachelor of Technology, Civil Engineering

May 2011

GPA: 3.76/4.00 (US Equivalent), Graduated First Class with Distinction

EXPERIENCE

Data Team Lead, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LIMITED, Edison, NJ, USA

May 2018-Aug. 2021

- Collaborated with customer to transform business data requirements for IT Cost Transparency module in TBMS
- Acted as liaison between IT and Corporate Finance to address analytics queries and remove financial roadblocks
- Maintained efficiency in RFP process by having a thorough understanding of all departmental information
- Coordinated with customers to review monthly billing worth \$6M+ and efficiently processed invoices in SAP Fieldglass
- Prioritized team activities to achieve and maintain a highly productive workforce in a deadline-driven environment

Data Analyst, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LIMITED, Chennai, India

Aug. 2016-Apr. 2018

- Streamlined data processing and established data transparency to provide team and data users with accessibility, consistency, and a transparent overview of 100+ data sets by creating Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs)
- Utilized APIs and custom functions in Apptio to streamline the month-end close process for the Bill of IT, resulting in a 40% reduction in processing time, from 5 weeks to 3 weeks
- Audited journal entries before being posted into SAP General ledger and reconciled IT accounts for corporate finance

IT Financial Analyst, TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LIMITED, Chennai, India

Sep. 2011-Jul. 2016

- Managed IT Project Management Operations (PMO) with projects worth \$5M+ and 400+ FTEs
- Collaborated with Business Relationship Managers in project planning activities, monitored and tracked actual revenue numbers, identified risks, and devised a mitigation plan to handle variance with budgeted amount
- Assessed billing leakage trend and executed a plan to reduce it, resulting in a 2% increase in profitability every quarter

ACADEMIC PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Assessed New Heritage Doll Company's finances by calculating financial metrics - NPV, IRR, and Payback Period

SKILLS

Advanced Excel – Data modeling (VLOOKUP, INDEX-MATCH, NESTED IFs, SUMPRODUCT, PIVOT Tables, Conditional Formatting, Data Tables), Microsoft Office suites (Excel, Outlook, PowerPoint, and Word), Apptio, Jira, SAP Fieldglass, R/R Studio for Financial Modeling

CERTIFICATIONS

Bloomberg Market Concepts (BMC), AZ-900: Azure Fundamentals, DP-900: Azure Data Fundamentals, APPTIO Elite TBMA, APPTIO Recognized TBMA, AINS 21

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Member of 'Apptio Community' and inducted into 'Wall of Fame' for optimizing data processing through automation